Guide to the Melville Cane Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series IV: Books and Periodicals
  - Subseries IV.1: Books & Periodicals By Or With Contributions By Cane
    - Allinson, Beverly & Alec Allinson, eds. Space Poems (Box 21)
    - The University of Kansas City Review, n.p., Spring 1951 (Box 21)
    - Stewart, Paul R. The Prarie Schooner Story (Box 21)
    - The American Bard, n.p., July, Aug, Sept 1957 (Box 21)
    - Phi Beta Kappa Bicentennial Banquet Program, n.p., 5 Dec 1976 (Box 21)
    - The New Mexico Quarterly Review, n.p., Spring 1961 (Box 21)
    - Foerster, Norman & Robert Falk, eds. American Poetry and Prose (Box 21)
    - First, Wesley, ed. Columbia Remembered (Box 21)
    - Columbia Grammar School Athletic Association Annual Field Day Program, n.p., 2 May 1895 (Box 22)
    - Harcourt, Brace, and World, Inc., from the public Annual Reports of In Art or Instruction (Box 22)
    - The Poetry Society of America Bulletin, n.p., May 1971 (Box 22)
    - Nowell, Elizabeth, ed. The Letters of Thomas Wolfe (Box 22)
    - De la Mora, Constancia In Place of Splendor (Box 22)
    - Smith, Harrison, ed. From Main Street to Stockholm: Letters of Sinclair Lewis (Box 22)
    - The New Yorker Book of Verse (Box 23)
    - McCord, David, ed. What Cheer: An Anthology of American and British Humorous & Witty Verse (Box 23)
    - Lask, Thomas, ed. The New York Times Book of Verse (Box 23)
    - Sheldon, William D. Arrivals and Departures (Box 23)
    - Westermark, Tory & Bryan Gooch, eds. Poetry is for People (Box 23)
    - Perry, Haydn, ed. Poetry Panorama 2 (Box 23)
    - Davidson, Gustav, ed. In Fealty to Apollo: Poetry Society of America, 1910-1950 (Box 23)
    - Harper's Weekly, clippings from, n.p., 20 May 1905 & 17 June 1905 (Box 23)
    - Grace, W.J. & J.C. Grace The Art of Communicating Ideas (Box 23)
    - Hepner, Arthur W. The Invitation to Learning Reader on Selected English Classics: Vol. 4, no. 1 (Box 23)
    - MacIver, R.M., ed. New Horizons in Creative Thinking: A Survey & Forecast (Box 23)
    - Cane, Melville, John Farrar & Louise Townsend Nicholl, eds. The Golden Year: The Poetry Society of American Anthology (1910-1960) (Box 23)
    - Angoff, Charles, Gustav Davidson, Hyacinthe Hill & A.M. Sullivan, eds. The Diamond Anthology (Box 23)
    - Hepner, Arthur W., ed. The Invitation to Learning Reader on Selected English Classics: Volume 4, no. 1 (Box 24)
    - Braithwaite, william S. & Margaret H. Carpenter, eds. Anthology of Magazine Verse for 1958 (Box 24)
    - Booth, Jack, ed. One Potato, Two Potato... (Box 24)
    - Stowe, Elaine & Grayce A. Ransom Drumbeats (Box 24)
    - Lyseng, Mary, compiled by Explore, Express: Alberta School Broadcasts 1977 (Box 24)
    - The Saturday Review of Literature, n.p., 11 Nov 1939; 25 Dec 1943; 27 Nov 1948; 28 Jan 1950; 1 July 1950; 26 Aug 1950; 25 Nov 1950; 31 March 1951; 21 July 1951 (Box 24)
    - The Commonweal, n.p., 22 Dec 1939 (Box 24)
    - Columbia Alumni News, n.p., July 1948 (Box 24)
    - The Saturday Review, n.p., 23 Feb 1952; 26 Dec 1953; 3 July 1954; 22 Jan 1955; 10 Dec 1955; 7 April 1956; 27 July 1963 (Box 24)
    - American Bar Association Journal, n.p., May 1947 (Box 24)
    - Psychological Prespectives, n.p., Spring 1972 (Box 24)
    - Spirit, n.p., Spring 1971 (Box 24)
    - Tomorrow, n.p., July 1947 (Box 24)
    - The Nation, n.p., 11 Dec 1929 (Box 24)
    - Best Articles and Stories, n.p., Jan 1958 (Box 24)
    - Columbia Today, n.p., June 1977 (Box 24)
    - Evening Tribune-Herald, excerpt from, Waco, TX, 1 March 1973 (Box 24)
    - Plotz, Helen Untune the Sky: Poems of Music and Dance (Box 25)
    - Cane, Melville All and Sundry: An Oblique Autobiography (Box 25)
    - Cane, Melville Bullet-Hunting and Other New Poems (Box 25)
    - Cane, Melville Poems: New and Selected (Box 25)
    - Cane, Melville Eloquent April (Box 25)
    - Cane, Melville A Wider Arc (Box 25)
    - Cane, Melville Tree in December (Box 25)
    - Cane, Melville To Build a Fire (Box 25)
    - Cane, Melville So That it Flower (Box 25)
    - Cane, Melville Making a Poem: An Inquiry into the Creative Process (Box 25)
    - Cane, Melville The First Firefly (Box 25)
    - Cane, Melville And Pastures New (Box 25)
    - Cane, Melville Behind Dark Spaces (Box 25)
    - Cane, Melville January Garden (Box 25)
    - New Democracy, n.p., 15 April 1933 (Box 26)
    - Life, n.p., 17 Aug 1922; 28 Aug 1924 (Box 26)
    - The Freeman, n.p., 24 May 1922 (Box 26)
    - Leslie's Monthly Magazine, n.p., Dec 1904 (Box 26)
    - The Guardian, n.p., Oct 1925 (Box 26)
    - Contempo, n.p., 21 Feb 1933 (Box 26)
    - The Atlantic Monthly, n.p., Feb 1968 (Box 26)
    - The Commonwealth, n.p., 1 April 1931; 3 Feb 1932 (Box 26)
    - Concerning Poetry, n.p., Fall 1968 (Box 26)
    - Grade Teacher, n.p., Jan 1967 (Box 26)
    - The Literary Review, n.p., Winter 1959-1960 (Box 26)
    - The New Mexico Quarterly Review, n.p., Summer 1945 (Box 26)
    - The American Bard, n.p., July, Aug, Sept 1957 (Box 26)
    - Munsey's Magazine, n.p., April 1906 (Box 26)
    - Harper's Monthly, n.p., July 1902 (Box 26)
    - Modern Verse, n.p., April 1941 (Box 26)
    - Law Review Digest, n.p., Sept/Oct 1952 (Box 26)
    - The New Freeman, n.p., 25 March 1931 (Box 26)
    - The New English Weekly, n.p., 19 May 1932; 8 March 1934 (Box 26)
    - The Nation, n.p., 9 Jan 1929; 28 Oct 1944; 10 March 1945 (Box 26)
    - The New Yorker, n.p., 29 Sept 1934; 28 Sept 1935; 14 May 1938; 25 Jan 1941; 4 July 1942; 24 Dec 1949; 22 Sept 1951 (Box 26)
    - Prarie Schooner, n.p., Summer 1944; Fall 1944; Summer 1945; Fall 1948; Spring 1951; Summer 1957 (Box 27)
    - The American Scholar, n.p., Spring 1935; Winter 1952-1953; Spring 1954; Autumn 1954; Spring 1957; Summer 1958; Summer 1960; Summer 1961; Spring 1964; Spring 1965; Autumn 1965; Spring 1966; Winter 1966-1967; Summer 1967; Autumn 1967; Winter 1968-1969; Autumn 1972 (Box 27)
    - Reader's Digest, n.p., April 1943 (Box 27)
    - The Poetry Chapbook, n.p., Fall 1948 (Box 27)
    - Coates, Doreen Twelve Months in the Year (Box 28)
    - The American Scholar, n.p., Spring 1963; Summer 1964; Winter 1968-1969; Winter 1969-1970; Spring 1970; Autumn 1970; Winter 1970-1971; Spring 1971; Autumn 1971 (Box 28)
    - The University Review--Kansas City, Kansas City, June 1965 (Box 28)
    - The American Pen, n.p., Summer 1971; Winter 1972 (Box 28)
    - The Yale Review, n.p., Winter 1934 (Box 28)
    - Columbia Forum, n.p., Winter 1970 (Box 28)
    - Judge, n.p., 16 Aug 1902 (Box 28)
    - Life, n.p., 17 Aug 1922 (Box 28)
    - Gilbert and Sullivan Quarterly, n.p., Fall 1936 (Box 28)
    - The American Scholar, excerpt from, n.p., Summer 1964 (Box 28)
    - Various clippings (Box 28)
    - The Virginia Quarterly Review, n.p., July 1932; Jan 1933 (Box 29)
    - The Yale Review, n.p., Winter 1930 (Box 29)
    - The University of Kansas City Review, n.p., Winter 1951; Autumn 1952; March 1955; Winter 1955; Spring 1958; Summer 1958; Spring 1959; Spring 1961; Summer 1961; Spring 1962; Autumn 1962 (Box 29)
    - The University Review--Kansas City, n.p., Summer 1965; Autumn 1965; Dec 1966; Autumn 1967; Spring 1969 (Box 29)
    - Southwest Review, n.p., Spring 1964 (Box 29)
    - Spirit, n.p., Nov 1965; Jan 1966; July 1966; Sept 1966 (Box 29)
    - The Literary Review, n.p., Autumn 1957 (Box 29)
    - Autograph Collectors' Journal, n.p., April 1950 (Box 29)
    - The Bookman, n.p., Jan/Feb 1932; March 1932 (Box 29)
    - The Dial, n.p., March 1925; May 1928 (Box 30)
    - The American Scholar, n.p., Autumn 1973 (Box 30)
    - The Writer, n.p., July 1944 (Box 30)
    - Best Articles and Stories, n.p., Jan 1958; Oct 1959 (Box 30)
    - Tomorrow, n.p., April1 942; Feb 1943; July 1947 (Box 30)
    - Scribner's, n.p., March 1932 (Box 30)
    - The Saturday Review of Literature, n.p., 22 June 1940; 14 Dec 1940; 29 Aug 1942; 11 Nov 1943; 25 Dec 1943; 1 Jan 1944; 9 June 1945; 15 Dec 1945; 14 June 1947; 19 June 1948; 27 Nov 1948; 5 Feb 1949; 2 April 1949; 7 Jan 1950; 28 Jan 1950; 26 Aug 1950; 1 July 1950; 31 March 1951; 24 Nov 1951 (Box 30)
    - The Saturday Review, n.p., 23 Feb 1952; 22 Aug 1953; 26 Dec 1953; 16 Jan 1954; 3 July 1954; 22 Jan 1955; 29 Oct 1955; 10 Dec 1955; 7 April 1956; 27 July 1963; 29 Jan 1966 (Box 30)
    - The Morningside, n.p., 19 Jan 1899; 1897 (entire year) (Box 31)
    - Columbia Literary Monthly, n.p., 1896-1897; 1897-1898; 1898-1899; 1899-1900 (Box 31)
  - Subseries IV.2: Inscribed Books
    - Sinclair, Upton, inscribed by A Catalogue of Books, Manuscripts, and Other Material from the Upton Sinclair Archives (Box 32)
    - Kubie, Lawrence S. Neurotic Distortion of the Creative Process (Box 32)
    - Kubie, Lawrence S. The Riggs Story (Box 32)
    - Nash, Ogden (not inscribed by author) Hard Lines (Box 32)
    - Erskine, John The Shadowed Hour (Box 32)
    - Liebman, Joshua Loth Peace of Mind (Box 32)
    - Cousins, Norman Modern Man is Obsolete (Box 32)
    - Beebe, Lucius Coctail Guide and Ladies Companion (Box 32)
    - Worthington, Marjorie The Strange World of Willie Seabrook (Box 32)
    - Sinclair, Mary Craig Southern Belle (Box 32)
    - Hellman, George S. The True Stevenson (Box 32)
    - Mumford, Lewis The Human Prospect (Box 32)
    - Decker, Clarence R. The Victorian Conscience (Box 33)
    - Decker, Clarence R. & Mary Bell Decker A Place of Light (Box 33)
    - Barrie, J.M. (not inscribed by author) Echoes of the War (Box 33)
    - Radin, Paul, ed. Crashing Thunder (Box 33)
    - Eiseley, Loren Francis Bacon and the Modern Dilemma (Box 33)
    - Palffy, Eleanor Largely Fiction (Box 33)
    - Bowes, Major Verses I like (Box 33)
    - Haberman, Helen Justice is a Woman (Box 33)
    - Yuzon, Amado M. The Citizen's Poems (Box 33)
    - Lanham, Edwin Thunder in the Earth (Box 33)
    - Houdini Miracle Mongers and their Methods (Box 34)
    - Eaton, Charles Edward Countermoves (Box 34)
    - Robbins, Harold Where Love Has Gone (Box 34)
    - Ross, David, ed. Poet's Gold (Box 34)
    - McKenney, Margaret The Savory Wild Mushroom (Box 34)
    - Meacham, Harry M. The Caged Panther (Box 34)
    - Raphael, Alice The Things That Are (Box 34)
    - Hayes, Albert M. & J. Laughlin, eds. (not inscribed by editors) A Wreath of Christmas Poems (Box 34)
    - Erskine, John Sonata (Box 34)
    - Jovanovich, William Now Barabbas (Box 34)
    - Raphael, Alice Now Barabbas (Box 34)
    - Kaufman, Helen L. Anvil Chorus (Box 34)
    - Seabrook, William No Hiding Place (Box 34)
    - Thompson, Dorothy Brown Subject to Change (Box 34)
    - Box, Curtis (not inscribed by author) I Too, Nicodemus (Box 35)
      [Review copy]
    - Bode, Carl The Half-World of American Culture (Box 35)
    - Campana, Dino (inscribed by Alice Raphael) Orphic Songs (Box 35)
    - Haydn, Hiram, inscribed by The Collected Poems of W.B. Yeats (Box 35)
    - Graves, Robert (inscribed by Margaret Naumberg) Oxford Addresses on Poetry (Box 35)
    - Goethe, trans. Alice Raphael Faust (Box 35)
    - Goethe, trans. Alice Raphael Parables (Box 35)
    - Haydn, Hiram, inscribed by Selected Essays of William Hazlitt (Box 35)
    - Cohn, Alfred E. No Retreat from Reason (Box 35)
    - Sullivan, A.M. Songs of the Musconetcong (Box 35)
    - Haydn, Hiram (not inscribed by author) Words and Faces (Box 35)
    - Mullins, Helene The Mirrored Walls (Box 36)
    - Bulosan, Carlos America is in the Heart (Box 36)
    - Kwock, C.H. and Vincent McHugh, trans. (inscribed by McHugh) Why I Live on the Mountain: Chinese Poems (Box 36)
    - Bottoms, Mollie Ruth Apple Tree in the Fall (Box 36)
    - Mercier, Vivian and David H. Greene, eds. 1000 Years of Irish Prose (Box 36)
    - Joyce, James Avery Justice at Work (Box 36)
    - Goethe, trans. Alice Raphael Faust (Box 36)
    - Cohn, Alfred E. Medicine, Science, and Art (Box 36)
    - Hollander, Barnett Slavery in America (Box 36)
    - Hinkle, Beatrice (inscribed by Alfred Harcourt) The Re-Creating of the Individual (Box 36)
    - Lewis, Arthur H. The Day They Shook the Plum Tree (Box 36)
    - Rosser, Annetta Hamilton An Offering of Song (Box 37)
    - Lyseng, Mary, compiled by (not inscribed) Explore, Express, Alberta School Broadcasts 1977 (Box 37)
    - Wollner, Gertrude Price Improvisation in Music (Box 37)
    - Sloane, Eric (inscribed by Robert Mareux) I Remember America (Box 37)
    - Thompson, Dorothy Once on Christmas (Box 37)
    - Van Doren, Mark Mark Van Doren on Great Poems of Western Literature (Box 37)
    - Lengyel, Cornel The Lookout's Letter (Box 37)
    - Salomon, I.L. Unit and Universe (Box 37)
    - Sullivan, A.M. Stars and Atoms Have No Size (Box 37)
    - Sullivan, A.M. The Bottom of the Sea (Box 37)
    - Sullivan, A.M. Elbows of the Sea (Box 37)
    - Sullivan, A.M. Psalms of the Prodigal (Box 37)
    - Sullivan, A.M. Tim Murphy, Morgan Rifleman (Box 37)
    - Sullivan, A.M. The Ballad of John Castner (Box 37)
    - Lewis, Mary Red Drumming in the Sun (Box 37)
    - Leach, Mary Stinton, compiled by (Inscribed by Poetry Society of Virginia) Lyric Virginia Today (Box 37)
    - Eberhart, Richard, Joseph J. Keith, Gordden Link & Madeline Mason (inscribed by Gordden Link) Quartet from The Golden Year (Box 37)
  - Subseries IV.3: Books About Cane & Family
    - Books about Cane and family (Box 38)
    - Books about Cane and family (Box 39)
- Series V: Medals
  - Medals (Box 40)
- Series VI. Manuscripts
  - Subseries VI.1: Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts and correspondence (1972-1975 gifts) (Box 41)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts and correspondence (1976 gift) (Box 42)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Box 43)
  - Series VI.2: Individual
    - All and Sundry (Box 44)
    - Eloquent April (Box 44)
    - Bow Tie (Box 45)
    - Eloquent April (Box 45)
    - First Fire Fly (Box 45)
    - Memories Recaptured (Box 45)
    - Poems to J. Proskauer (Box 45)
    - All and Sundry - correspondence, jacket, (68 items) (Box 46)
    - All and Sundry - original ms., typescript, (3 items) (Box 46)
    - American Scholar - essay in - correspondence, (31 items) (Box 46)
    - American Scholar - essay in - typescript, reprint, (2 items) (Box 46)
    - And Pastures New - edited ms., (4 items & complete text) (Box 46)
    - And Pastures New - galley proofs, (5 items) (Box 46)
    - And Pastures New - ms., galley proof, (4 items) (Box 46)
    - Behind Dark Spaces - work sheets, proof, (2 items) (Box 47)
    - Behind Dark Spaces - edited ms., rough proof, (2 items) (Box 47)
    - Bullet-Hunting - correspondence, (67 items) (Box 47)
    - Bullet-Hunting - typescript, proof, (3 items) (Box 47)
    - Bullet-Hunting and Other New Poems - corrected ms., page proof, (2 items) (Box 47)
    - "Invitation to Learning" - on Swinburne, with Trilling, (2 items) (Box 47)
    - January Garden - reviews, correspondence, (39 items) (Box 47)
    - January Garden - typescript, galley proof, page proof, (3 items) (Box 47)
    - "KTLN Book Reporter" - radio program, Denver, August 1948, (1 item) (Box 47)
    - Making a Poem - corrected ms., galley proof, (5 items) (Box 47)
    - Making a Poem - correspondence, reviews, (106 items) (Box 47)
    - Making a Poem - printer's ms., (1 item) (Box 47)
    - Man from Main Street - reviews, correspondence, (22 items) (Box 48)
    - Misc. documents - manuscript, (7 items) (Box 48)
    - Misc. documents - printed, (14 items) (Box 48)
    - Misc. documents - typed, (31 items) (Box 48)
    - "New Horizons for Poetry" - correspondence, (94 items) (Box 48)
    - "New Horizons for Poetry" - original ms., typescript, (2 items) (Box 48)
    - Poems: New and Selected - correspondence, (26 items) (Box 48)
    - Poetry Society of America - misc. items, (5 items) (Box 48)
    - Poetry Society of Virginia - address, correspondence, (8 items) (Box 48)
    - So That It Flower - corrected galley proof, (1 item) (Box 49)
    - So That It Flower - corrected galley proof, page proof, jacket & copy, (6 items) (Box 49)
    - So That It Flower - correspondence, (50 items) (Box 49)
    - So That It Flower - edited ms., galley proof, (4 items) (Box 49)
    - So That It Flower - work sheets, (8 items) (Box 49)
    - To Build a Fire - correspondence, (86 items) (Box 50)
    - To Build a Fire - ms., galley proof, page proof, jacket, (4 items) (Box 50)
    - Univ. of Kansas City - Lectures, (8 items) (Box 50)
    - Univ. of Kansas City - Lectures - correspondence, clippings, (10 items) (Box 50)
    - Univ. of Kansas City Review - "How 'Humbly, Wildly' was Born" - p. copies, (10 items) (Box 50)
    - Univ. of Kansas City Review - articles by and about, correspondence, (26 items) (Box 50)
    - "Why Ask for Permission?" - correspondence, (11 items) (Box 50)
    - A Wider Arc - correspondence, (34 items) (Box 50)
    - A Wider Arc - edited ms., (1 item) (Box 50)
    - A Wider Arc - reviews, (2 items) (Box 50)
    - "Within the Dark" - correspondence, (29 items) (Box 50)
    - "Within the Dark" - ms., work sheets, (4 items) (Box 50)
- Series VII: Subject Files
  - Subseries VII.1: Columbia University
    - Address on "John Erskine" - Friends of the Columbia Libraries, (21 items) (Box 51)
    - Alumni publications, (2 items) (Box 51)
    - Class Day; Commencement, (8 items) (Box 51)
    - Clubs; Societies, (14 items) (Box 51)
    - College and Law School records, (11 items) (Box 51)
    - Columbia Grammar School, records, (2 items) (Box 51)
    - Correspondence, (18 items) (Box 51)
    - Commencement, Dean's Day - speeches and presentations, (5 items) (Box 51)
    - Dance and dinner programs, (7 items) (Box 51)
    - Miscellaneous items, (13 items) (Box 51)
    - Columbia University Musical Society - The Governor's Vrouw, (9 items) (Box 51)
    - Printed report, (5 items) (Box 51)
    - University Medal for Excellence, (47 items) (Box 51)
    - University Publications with writings by Cane, (2 items) (Box 51)
    - Woodberry Convocation, 1948, (22 items) (Box 51)
  - Subseries VII.2: Various Subjects
    - Article by Hiram Haydn in American Scholar - correspondence about, (27 items) (Box 52)
    - Birthday dinner - 60th - correspondence, lists, (49 items) (Box 52)
    - Birthday dinner - 80th - correspondence, (23 items) (Box 52)
    - Jovanovich, William, (4 items) (Box 52)
    - Law records, (7 items) (Box 52)
    - Ms. letters to Alfred E. Cohn, (44 items) (Box 52)
    - Material about Cane, (7 items) (Box 52)
    - Misc. documents, (13 items) (Box 52)
    - Notebook - 1897-1912 - poems, printed and ms. written and loose, (16 items) (Box 52)
    - Notebook - 1925-1926 - work sheets & complete poems in ms., (1 item) (Box 52)
    - Notebook - containing poems by various authors, (1 item) (Box 52)
    - Pictures, (5 items) (Box 52)
    - The Sun - correspondence, (2 items) (Box 52)
    - Yale College records, (4 items) (Box 52)
    - Musical Settings of his poems, (8 items) (Box 52)
    - Misc. letters to Cane, (9 items) (Box 52)
- Series VIII: Oversized Material
  - Scrapbooks (Box 32)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 33)
  - (Box 14-13-10)